"Spices to Boost GLP-1"
If you have people
eat the same meal,
but chew each bite
either 15 times or 40 times,
the blood levels
of the appetite-suppressing
hormone GLP-1
in the blood stream
are higher
after 40 chews than 15,
and those who chewed 40 times
ended up consuming
about 75 fewer calories
than the 15-time chewers.
The researchers suggest
that chewing more
may help people
keep their weight down.
Okay, but who wants to sit there
and count how many times
they chew?
What if you just eat
chewier foods?
What if you have people
eat shredded cabbage,
which requires a lot of chewing,
or the same amount
of pureed cabbage;
same food, but requiring
different amounts of chewing?
GLP-1 blood levels were higher
in the shredded cabbage
chewing group
than the pureed cabbage
non-chewing one,
at 45, 60, and 90 minutes,
at least initially.
The researchers were careful
to make sure
both groups ate
at the same rate,
because eating
even the same food more slowly
can result in a greater
GLP-1 response.
Researchers had people
eat the same amount of ice cream
over a period of either
five minutes or 30 minutes,
and those who ate
the exact same amount
of the same food more slowly
experienced a significant boost
in GLP-1 levels in their blood
for hours after the meal,
about a 30 percent bump overall.
On average, the participants
were overweight,
but a lot slimmer
than your average American.
What about essentially
re-doing the same study,
but with obese individuals
who could really use
the extra GLP-1 boost?
And here we go.
As you can see from the title,
the researchers found
disparate results
when they tested
obese adolescents
versus obese adults.
With the obese teens,
researchers saw the same outcome
as they did with
the overweight adults;
a significantly higher
GLP-1 response
after slower eating.
But the rate of eating
didn’t seem to matter
in obese adults.
Same thing with satiety.
Obese adolescents felt fuller,
more satiated for longer
when eating more slowly,
but speed of eating
didn’t seem to matter
in the adults with obesity.
But, at least for some,
more chewing
and eating more slowly
may raise GLP-1 levels,
no matter what’s consumed.
But are there certain foods
that specifically boost GLP-1?
In my last video,
I went through a bunch of foods,
beverages, and supplements
that don’t appear to work,
but there are
a few spices that might.
Volunteers were served
rice with vegetable curry
made with three different
doses of spices.
The bland control meal
had no spices at all,
just tomato puree with eggplant.
The low-spice meal added
a tablespoon of curry spices,
plus onions, garlic, and ginger.
And the third variation,
the high-spice curry,
had double the spices,
two tablespoons.
The spices were turmeric,
coriander seeds, cumin seeds,
dried Indian gooseberry powder--
also known as amla--
cayenne pepper,
cinnamon, and cloves
mixed in the ratio of eight
to four to four to four,
to two to one to one,
respectively.
And the average bump
in GLP-1 blood concentration
for those eating
both the low-spice
and high-spice meals
were 17 and 32 percent higher,
compared to the bland
control meal without the spices.
About the same calories
and macronutrients,
but the spicier meals
raised GLP-1 levels higher.
But which spice was it?
Ginger compounds boosts
GLP-1 in mice but not rats,
and in humans, we appeared
to react more like the rats:
no effect.
For many of the other spices,
there isn’t even in vitro data,
but rather only in silico,
meaning just some kind
of computer modeling
that didn’t actually test
anything in a biological system.
But we do have data on curcumin,
the yellow compound
found in the spice turmeric.
This study used
180 milligrams of curcumin,
which is the amount found in
a single teaspoon of turmeric.
The researchers also tested
fish oil supplements,
but while the fish oil failed,
the curcumin
reduced the blood sugar spike
after a meal,
which is something both
GLP-1 and GLP-1 drugs can do,
though GLP-1 levels
weren’t directly measured.
The researchers suggest
it may be a GLP-1 effect,
since curcumin
stimulates GLP-1 in rodents,
as well as cells
in a Petri dish,
but there hasn’t been
a human study until now.
Six months
of curcumin supplementation
led to a quadrupling
of GLP-1 levels,
compared to placebo.
Okay, so, turmeric may help.
What about cinnamon?
Scandinavian researchers
gave people rice pudding
with and without
one or three grams of cinnamon,
which is about
a third of a teaspoon,
or a full teaspoon.
And those getting
the full teaspoon of cinnamon
more than doubled
the GLP-1 bump-from-baseline
compared to the control pudding
without the cinnamon.
So, that’s another spice
that may work,
though people didn’t report
feeling any more satiated
eating the cinnamon-y pudding
compared to plain.
And finally, the third spice
to boost GLP-1 in humans?
Cayenne pepper.
What happened
when a half a teaspoon
of cayenne pepper
was added to a meal?
Over a short period of time--
15 minutes--
a single spicy meal
significantly increased
blood levels of GLP-1.
Though,
like in the cinnamon study,
this did not appear to translate
into them feeling any fuller,
but the researcher
didn’t measure
actual subsequent food intake.